<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first addresses to His Excellencie the Lord General, with the Assembly of elders elected by him and his Council for the management of the affairs of this Commonwealth; as also, to all the cordial officers and souldiers under his command. Containing certain rules &amp; directions how to advance the kingdome of Jesus Christ over the face of the whole earth. By John Spittlehouse, a late member of the Army, and a servant to the saints of the most high God, whose kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and whom all dominions shall serve and obey, Dan. 7.27.</title>
            <author>Spittlehouse, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93700</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5008</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E703_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203632</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863518</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863518</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115722</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93700)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115722)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 108:E703[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first addresses to His Excellencie the Lord General, with the Assembly of elders elected by him and his Council for the management of the affairs of this Commonwealth; as also, to all the cordial officers and souldiers under his command. Containing certain rules &amp; directions how to advance the kingdome of Jesus Christ over the face of the whole earth. By John Spittlehouse, a late member of the Army, and a servant to the saints of the most high God, whose kingdom is an everlasting kingdom, and whom all dominions shall serve and obey, Dan. 7.27.</title>
                  <author>Spittlehouse, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. for himself and Richard Moone, at the seven stars in Paul's Church-yard, neer the great North-door.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Postscript, D4r: If any desire the book, they may have it at Giles Calverts shop at the Black-spread Eagle, at the west end of Pauls.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 5".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115722:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The firſt ADDRESSES TO His EXCELLENCIE the Lord General, with the ASSEMBLY of ELDERS elected by him and his Council for the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the affairs of this COMMONWEALTH; As alſo, to all the cordial Officers and Souldiers under his command. CONTAINING Certain RULES &amp; DIRECTIONS how to advance the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt over the face of the whole earth. By <hi>John Spittlehouſe,</hi> a late Member of the Army, and a ſervant to the Saints of the moſt high God, <hi>whoſe Kingdom is an everlaſting kingdom, and whom all dominions ſhall ſerve and obey,</hi> Dan. 7. 27.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut printer's device for Richard Moone in the form of a rebus (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
               <p>Richard</p>
               <figDesc>depiction of a man in the moon</figDesc>
               <p>In Paules Church Yard Att The</p>
               <figDesc>depiction of seven stars</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for himſelf and <hi>Richard Moone,</hi> at the ſeven ſtars in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, neer the great North-door. 1653.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115722:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115722:2"/>
            <head>To his Excellency the Lord General <hi>Cromwel.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath not been out of a fantaſtick humour, as ſome think, that I did in my late warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing piece, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> compare you to <hi>Moſes,</hi> or that I went about in the leaſt to claw you, but that I was aſſured, that as the Lord had decreed that his people in theſe latter days ſhould have <hi>judges</hi> as at the firſt, ſo likewiſe Rulers as at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which doubtleſs had reference, as well unto <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his power and authority, whom it is evident, did in Gods ſtead ſelect Judges for the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which Judges did not in the leaſt impower <hi>Moſes,</hi> or add any authority unto him, but contrariwiſe, he unto them, as he was the immediate Miniſter of God: and therefore beware how you receive any Commiſſion from this preſent Aſſembly, either as to your relation as a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, or upon any other account whatſoever; for in ſo doing, you cleerly deny Jeſus Chriſt to be King of this Nation: ſo that you are to make no further uſe of them, then to appoint them to deſtroy Antichriſt in his Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonical and Prieſtly power, with their appendancies, and to advance the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, with his Laws and Ordinances (to which purpoſe the whole ſcope of this Treatiſe tendeth) which when you have once put in an orderly poſture, that then you would in like manner order them their ſeveral ſtations in the Commonwealth, for <hi>Moſes</hi> did not keep the Elders of
<pb facs="tcp:115722:3"/> 
               <hi>Iſrael</hi> continually together in a lump, but diſperſed them as occaſion was offered, making the ſame Elders he had choſen, heads over the people, <hi>&amp;c. Exod.</hi> 18. 25, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> reſerving the chief management of affairs to himſelf, which certainly was not barely to himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but with the aſſiſtance of his faithful Officers of war about him, of which I hope you may be plentiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupplyed, ſo that the Church or kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt may appear in its now proper poſture (viz. <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible as an Army with Banners,</hi> unto all the Nations upon the face of the whole earth. And therefore your and their poſture will not now be to ſit ſtill, and ſing a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiem</hi> unto your ſouls, ſaying, <hi>Soul, take thine eaſe, eat, drink, and be merry, thou haſt goods laid up for many yeers;</hi> but to perſevere in the work of the Lord, in forraign parts, and not to make peace with the <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> or any other Nation which the Lord hath a controverſie with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, and who are deſigned to deſtruction, to the end you may reſt quietly upon your beds of Ivory. For if you do, know aſſuredly, that as you have been parallel'd with <hi>Moſes</hi> in your acts of valour, ſo you ſhall likewiſe die in Mount-Nebo, which the form or Model of the houſe you live in, is not much unlike: but I hope the Lord hath not onely intended to ſhew you the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> but will alſo lead you over the flood <hi>Iordan,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Land of the <hi>Canaanites,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>(viz.</hi> over the Nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Seas, into <hi>Holland, France,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, to the end you may pluck up all Antichriſtian power whatſoever doth oppoſe Jeſus Chriſt in the leaſt, which is the earneſt expectation of Truths, and</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your honors ſervant, <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="addresses">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115722:3"/>
            <head>The firſt ADDRESSES, to his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency the Lord General, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable and well-beloved,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a ſaying not ſo ancient as true, <hi>That the right beginning of an action, extendeth to the half accompliſhment thereof.</hi> And therefore in as much as Providence hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected you ſervants in his preſent deſigne, it will be very requiſite that you know before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand what your work is, to the end you may not be enſnared by ignorance to your infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, as many of your predeceſſors have been.</p>
            <p>Knowledge (ſaith one) is that underſtanding which we have of our Creator, as alſo of his works and will; and likewiſe of our ſelves: in reference to the laſt of which, it is reported, that over the Temple of <hi>Apollo</hi> the God of the <hi>Paynims,</hi> there was this inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on engraven in letters of Gold, <hi>Noſce teipſum;</hi> Signifying, that he that would have admittance there, <hi>muſt firſt learn to know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> and could not otherwiſe be received. Yea ſuch excellency was aſcribed by the Athenians to ſuch knowledge, as that they preſented <hi>Pompey the Great</hi> with this Motto, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou art ſo much a God, as thou knoweſt thy ſelf to be a Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115722:4"/>
            <p> And doubtleſs the Spirit of God did not in vain record <hi>Moſes</hi> to be found in an Ark of Bull-ruſhes, and after that to keep ſheep, as alſo <hi>Joſhua</hi> to be <hi>Moſes</hi> ſervant, <hi>Gideon</hi> a Thraſher, <hi>Jephtah</hi> the ſon of an Harlot, <hi>David</hi> a Shepherd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but that he did foreſee it as requiſite to put them in minde of their <hi>once low condition,</hi> as of their <hi>valiant atchievements,</hi> tending to their <hi>Exaltations.</hi> Yea ſo willing was the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> to have ſuch ſhamefac't things made manifeſt, as that ſhe becometh her own Herald, to blaze the ſame to all poſterities, as where ſhe ſaith,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My ſoul doth magnifie the Lord, and my ſpirit hath rejoyced in God my Saviour, for he hath regarded the Low Eſtate of his handmaid,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for he that is mighty, hath done to me great things, and holy is his Name, and his Mercy is on them that fear him from generation to generation: he hath ſhewed ſtrength with his Arm, he hath ſcattered the proud in the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their hearts, he hath put down the Mighty from their ſeats, and exalted them Of Low Degree. He hath filled the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry with good things, and the rich he hath ſent empty away. He hath holpen his ſervant Iſrael, in remembrance of his Mercies, as he ſpake to our forefathers, to</hi> Abraham, <hi>and to his ſeed for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore think not much with me, that I put you in minde how the like Mercies are now confer'd upon many of you, when you were in as low a condition, as the aforeſaid <hi>Mary;</hi> Even whilſt you were Brewers, and Brewers ſervants, Shoo-makers, Taylors, and ſuch other Mechanick men. Yea, I am very confident, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of you thirteen or fourteen yeers ago, did little think you ſhould ever have attained to ſuch honour and wealth, as you are now by Providence dignified withal.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, Miſtake me not, as that by theſe expreſſions I ſhould in the leaſt go about to blaſt any of your reputations, my intent herein being only that I might preſent my ſelf here unto you, as the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſerviter,</hi> of whom it is reported, that in the midſt of all their jollity in their feaſts, he was accuſtomed to preſent amongſt them <hi>a dead mans Scull,</hi> whereby they might be made ſenſible, what their end ſhould be. Yea the Scripture it ſelf preſenteth the Kingly Prophet with the like Motto, to all perſons dignified with honour, where he ſaith, <hi>I ſaid ye are Gods, but ye ſhall die like men, and</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115722:4"/> 
               <hi>become as one of the Princes;</hi> as alſo where he ſaith, <hi>Man that is in honour, and underſtandeth not, is like the beaſts that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And without controverſe, certain it is, that proſperity doth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally prove no better then an honyed poyſon ſweet and pleaſant, but exceeding dangerous: it is a ſlippery paſſage, wherein Men ought to take ſure foot-hold, there being no time wherein men do more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently forget God, as precedent examples have plentifully taught, and daily experience doth yet teach; inſtance the late King, and the Nobility which were his favourites; as as alſo your late predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in Parliament, as yet freſh in your memories; beſides which, we have a moſt remarkable preſident of <hi>Iſrael</hi> that Ancient people of God, <hi>who albeit they were the Lords portion, and the lot of his inheritance, yea albeit he had found them in a deſart land, and in a waſte howling wilderneſs; though he had led them about, and inſtructed them, and had kept them as the apple of his eye, and had born them up as upon the wings of an Eagle, and had made them to ride upon the high places of the field, ſo that they did eat the increaſe of the field, as alſo to ſuck hony out of the Rock, and oyl out of the flinty Rock; as alſo to eat Butter of Kine, and milke of ſheep, with the fat of lambs and Rams of the breed of Baſhan; of Goats, with the fat of kidneys, and with the fineſt of the wheat, as alſo to drink the pure blood of the Grape: yea, albeit he had reproved Kings for their ſakes, and ſlain mighty Kings;</hi> Yet we ſee, the event of all theſe mercies produced onely <hi>a wanton carriage</hi> from the aforeſaid people, to the Donet thereof: for the Text ſaith, that <hi>when they were ſo made fat, then, even then, did Jeſurun kick up the heel; then, even then did they forſake God that made them, and lightly eſteemed the Rock of their ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, dear friends, inaſmuch as theſe things <hi>are written for inſtruction,</hi> I humbly deſire you would ſet this <hi>preſident</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually before your eyes, inaſmuch as many amongſt you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as great and ample favours from God, as them Iſraelites.</p>
            <p>Take heed therefore, I intreat you, and be very circumſpect over your actions, whilſt the like radiant beams of Providence ſhine ſo gloriouſly upon you; Whilſt the illuſtrious beauty of your preſent condition hath ſuch an influence upon your vaſſals; whilſt the Lord
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115722:5"/> hath furniſhed you with all things, even to the utmoſt deſires of your hearts.</p>
            <p>As by giving you Houſes to live in which you built not, Gardens and Orchards which you planted not, with vaſt treaſures got by the ſweat of other mens brows, with gorgeous apparel and titles of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, which formerly you would have been aſhamed of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> take heed therefore, I humbly entreat you; for now, even now, are you car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed up to the very higheſt pinacle of temptation, and therefore your condition is ſo much the more dangerous, by how much the talleſt Cedar is more ſubject to a ſtorm then the loweſt ſhrub: and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it was out of ſome ſuch conſideration, that <hi>Agur</hi> deſired neither poverty nor riches.</p>
            <p>Stand therefore valiantly upon your guard, by bridling your affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and compoſing all your actions according to the rule and ſquare of Gods Word; and that as well in things of civil concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as of ſpiritual; you having there as plain directions for the one as for the other <hi>(viz.</hi> in poynt of civil Laws, as in publike worſhip, which this following Treatiſe will fully evidence) and therefore be well aſſured, that by how much you digreſs therefrom, either to the right hand or to the left, by ſo much will the Lord diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ovvn you, by ſo much will he extirpate your memorials from under heaven, by ſo much will your very name rot upon the face of the earth, as hath been manifeſted in your late predeceſſors; which the Lord in much mercy prevent, by giving you an abſolute and cordial reſolution to keep cloſe to all his holy Laws and Commandments, which he hath given in charge to be obſerved and put in execution. But to the thing intended.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, I preſume you are not ignorant for what you are here aſſembled. I hope it is to accompliſh the grand deſign of your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Lord and Maſter Jeſus Chriſt, in theſe Overturning, Overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Overturning days, and that with all exactneſs, according to the rules of direction preſcribed in his ſacred word, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That to the utmoſt of your power you will endeavour the ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt to the uttermoſt parts of the earth, <hi>viz.</hi> until he hath taken the ſame into his poſſeſſion, until he hath broken all the heathen and Antichriſtian Nations with a rod of iron, and daſhed them in pieces like a Potters veſſel, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 8, 9. until the Saints of the moſt high God have taken the Kingdom and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115722:5"/> Dominion, and greatneſs of the kingdom under the whole heaven into their poſſeſſion. Yea, untill all the kingdoms and dominions, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the face of the earth, do ſerve and obey him, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. untill he hath put down all Rule, and all Authority and Power under his feet (but what is properly his own) 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 24, &amp;c. untill all the Kings of the earth be bound in chains, and their Nobles with linkes of iron; untill he hath made all his foes his footſtool, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 13. untill God the Father hath put all things in ſubjection under him; yea, untill he hath left nothing to put under him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 9. untill he hath executed the judgement upon the great Red Dragon the beaſt, with the old ſtrumpet termed Myſtery <hi>Babylon</hi> the Great, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of harlots and abomination of the earth; who is ſaid to be drunk with the blood of the Saints, and with the blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Jeſus, <hi>Revel.</hi> cap. 12. and 17. <hi>(viz.)</hi> untill you have avenged the blood of them that lye ſlaine under the Altar; untill you have deſtroyed them which deſtroyed the Saints; until you have rewarded <hi>Babylon</hi> as ſhe hath rewarded you; untill you have doubled unto her double according to her works; until the cup that ſhe and her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-harlots hath filled, be filled to them double; untill by how much they have glorified themſelves, and lived deliciouſly, that ſo much tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſorrow be given unto them, as in the book of the <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> is cleerly commanded, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 6, 7, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen, If theſe be your intentions, then ride on and proſper; but if otherwiſe, then ſudden deſtruction ſhall come upon you una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares, as it did upon your late predeceſſors; but I hope better things of you, though I thus ſpeak: but nevertheleſs, inaſmuch as the Lord hath been pleaſed to call out this our Nation as a Theater to act a preſident of what he intends to do in all the Nations under the cope of heaven, it behoveth you therefore, before you ſet your ſelves in the ſeat of judicature in relation to other Nations, to begin at home. And that according to the Apoſtles directions, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 1, 3. where he ſaith, <hi>Thou art inexcuſable, O man, whoſoever thou art that judgeſt, for wherein thou judgeſt another, thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneſt thy ſelf, for thou that judgeſt doſt the ſame thing.</hi> Againe, thinkeſt thou this, O man, which judgeſt them that do ſuch things, and doſt the ſame, that thou ſhalt eſcape the judgment of God?</p>
            <p>Which that you may do, I ſhall take upon me, by Divine aſſiſtance,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115722:6"/> to ſet before you the grand obſtructions which interpoſe the will of God herein; which until removed, I do hereby aver, that the Lord of hoſts will never deſiſt his dreadful breaking in pieces of this and all other powers whatſoever, that ſhall in the leaſt contradict the ſame.</p>
            <p>That then which the Lord Chriſt expects from you at this your Convention, is,</p>
            <p>1. That you would <hi>make his foes his footſtool:</hi> which, certain I am can be no otherwiſe effected, then by plucking up all thoſe plants which the heavenly Father hath not planted, (and that as well root as branch) which I do affirm to be the Prieſts and Lawyers of this Nation, or otherwiſe the devouring locuſts and caterpillers of this Nation: <hi>viz.</hi> all ſuch Prieſts (under what name or title ſoever dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied or diſtinguiſhed) as ſhall be found in <hi>Babylon, viz.</hi> all ſuch as have not diſclaimed their Rantiſm and Ordination, which they have received from the Popes of <hi>Rome</hi> and their ſucceſſors, inaſmuch as they are of the ſame lineage and off-ſpring of the grand harlot of <hi>Rome,</hi> mentioned <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 5. where ſhe is termed <hi>The mother of harlots.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore I earneſtly deſire that you would without partiality conſider (and that moſt ſeriouſly) whether the preſent Prieſthood of this Nation be <hi>Jure Divino:</hi> and if they be not, that then you vvould deal with them as you and your predeceſſors have done with the old Harlot, and her eldeſt daughter Prelacie; which you muſt either conclude to be of the off-ſpring of the aforeſaid Whore, or otherwiſe it muſt conſequently follow, that you have done the Prieſts of that Judgement much injury.</p>
            <p>But if you and your predeceſſors did include prelacy as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, and ſo not <hi>jure divino,</hi> and therefore did paſs your ſentence upon her, then it will follow in the next place to conſider, in what reſpect you ſo adjudged her, as whether in point of conſtitution (as by rantizing of Infants, and thereby erecting Nationall Churches, in imitation of her aforeſaid Mother) or in point of ordination, derived in like manner as aforeſaid; or in point of maintenance, or perſecuting principle; or in point of doctrine, or ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Now if you judged her for ſome or all of theſe, which you muſt unavoidably do, then it will follow, that whoſoever is found guilty of the like crime, muſt incurre the like puniſhment: and therefore if I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115722:6"/> ſhall prove that the Presbyterian Prieſts of this Nation are ſo guilty, as aforeſaid, they muſt conſequently be judged accordingly.</p>
            <p>Which that they are, <hi>is proved,</hi> (1.) In that all men know, it is their daily practiſe to rantize Infants to all ends and purpoſes as did the prelates. (2.) In that their ordination is alſo unvoidably derived from the Biſhops, who received it from the Popes of <hi>Rome.</hi> (3.) In that Tithes are of the ſame lineage with Monkeries, Abbies, and Frie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, as alſo with Biſhopricks, and the like Popiſh maintenance. (4.) In that they are likewiſe of the ſame perſecuting Principle, witneſs that Ordinance which they procured of the late Parliament made in <hi>Anno</hi> not yet repealed. (5.) In point of Doctrine: I appeale to any knowing man, whether the Presbyterian Prieſts are not as orthodox as they: ſo that there remaineth nothing wherein they differ from the Prelates, unleſs in a few ceremonies, as the wearing of the ſurpliſs, croſs in Rantiſme, or Sprinkling of Infants, Pictures in glaſs windowes, or Common-prayer-book, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So that the iſſue will be, whether you or your predeceſſors did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate prelacy for the eſſentiall, or circumſtantiall part thereof: if for the circumſtantiall part only <hi>(viz)</hi> for the aforeſaid ceremonies, then I deſire to know why all, or many of you do not affect Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſeeing they uſe no ſuch ceremony as aforeſaid; yea doubtleſs you are exceedingly much to blame for oppoſing that Church-government: ſo that you can no otherwiſe excuſe your ſelves of matter of fact a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that government, but by applying the antichriſtian part of Presbytery to its eſſentials, <hi>(viz</hi> their conſtituting of National Churches by rantizing of Infants.) (2.) Their Popiſh Ordination re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from Biſhops, and their Babyloniſh maintenance by Tithes, (which very maintenance doth as fully prove them to be the Off-ſpring of the Romiſh Harlot, as the aforeſaid Biſhopricks, Frieries, Abbies, and Monkeries, doth declare the ſaid parties that poſſeſs them to be deſcended from <hi>Rome</hi> as aforeſaid,) and if ſo, then I would gladly know of any of you, whether antichriſtianiſm ought to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in its eſſentials, and puniſhed in its circumſtantials; and if it ought not to be ſo ſupported, then I would know wherefore a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Prieſt ſhould be continued more then the Biſhops and their generation.</p>
            <p>And if not, then will not Tythes of courſe fall into your hands to diſpoſe of, as well as the aforeſaid Munkeries, Abbies, and Frieries
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115722:7"/> fell into the hands of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and other the Kings of this Nation, as being things dedicated to ſuperſtitious uſes, or at leaſt in that capacity, as Biſhops, Deans and Chapters Lands was ſeaſed on by the late Parliament, the one being every way as much forfeited as the other, if you will judge of the intentionall deſire they have had of a long time to ſee you ruined, as I am well aſſured you are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of: but my deſire is not, that you would ſo deal with them, as they are enemies to your ſelves, but as it is an apparent ſupport of antichriſt in this Nation; in which ſence you are every whit as much bound in duty and ſervice to Jeſus Chriſt, to deal by the preſent Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Prieſts, as you have done with the prelatical; which I hope your predeceſſors did more out of conſcience, becauſe they appeare Antichriſtians, then any ways out of private revenge of any injury received by them; albeit, had they ſo done, it had been juſtifiable in the fight of God, in that both they and you were and are authorized and commanded ſo to do, as in the aforementioned texts of Scripture, of <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 6, 7. <hi>viz.</hi> by a duplified retaliation of injury offered by ſuch-like antichriſtian brats; as alſo inaſmuch as the Lord hath ſo evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declared his deteſtation againſt the Presbyterian Prieſts, as ever he did againſt the prelatical, witneſs <hi>Scotland</hi> in general, if that which hath been done in <hi>England,</hi> be not ſufficient to prove the ſame.</p>
            <p>So that it will not be only a manifeſt declaring of your ſelves to be antagoniſts to Jeſus Chriſt in his work now before you, but it will be every way as dangerous to this Common-wealth, to continue ſuch Prieſts to preach therein, as it would be for you to permit the conquered enemy to beare armes again amongſt you.</p>
            <p>Gentlemen,</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>I know theſe will be accounted hard ſayings by many of you, yea ſo hard, as that ye are not able to bear them: I know alſo, your reply will be, that they are men of a Godly life and converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore it would be a cruel thing to deal ſo hardly by them, inaſmuch as many of them have great families, as alſo in that they have no other way to ſubſiſt on for a livelyhood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> I agree with you in all theſe, as to a ſeemingly-hard mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: but inaſmuch as the people of God are in <hi>Babylon,</hi> Rev. 18. 4. and inaſmuch as they have been ſo earneſtly ſollicited by the Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of God to depart or come out thereof, but will not, it is not the will of God that they ſhould be ſpared for their godly life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115722:7"/> or for that they have great families, and no other way of livelyhood, but that in caſe they ſhall refuſe to come when called, that then they ſhall be puniſhed even as Babylonians, as in the ſame verſe. Again, what reſpect hath been made to the prelates, and their Brood?</p>
            <p>Obj. But you will ſay, <hi>The Biſhops had great eſtates left them, but theſe have but from hand to mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> That is becauſe many of them have lived as in <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 7. <hi>viz.</hi> more like Knights then <hi>Corridons,</hi> and their wives like Ladies then <hi>Phillida's,</hi> and ſo conſequently their Children, with their ſerving-man and waiting-maid; it is becauſe with her Siſter prelacy, and the old baud her mother, they have fared deliciouſly, thinking they ſhould ſit as queens for ever, without controle, feeling no ſorrow. But ſome may ſay,</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Many Cavalier Prieſts are yet continued, albeit they have formerly been in actuall arms againſt the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> That was either a manifeſt miſcarryage of the Parliament, or otherwiſe becauſe they made Friends, or that Cameleon-like, by changing themſelves into every judgement that retaineth Tithes. And hence it is that many Papiſts have formerly pretended themſelves to be Prelaticants, many Prelaticants to become pretended Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and many Presbyterians pretended Independants: for what are ſuch now under the notion of Independants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that yet juſtifie the Antichriſtian eſſentiall of rantizing of Infants, when they ſeem to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn national Churches by their gathered congregations? can any rational man then imagine but that ſuch perſons are either Papiſts, Prelaticants, or Presbyterians; or that they do it meerly to creep into the favour of the Magiſtrate, by cloſing with his opinion, to the end they might be yet maintained by ſuch Romiſh proviſions? witneſs many Independents in and about <hi>London,</hi> who to keeep up Tithes, will lecture it to them they account the world; and to keep in with the Magiſtrate, will alſo have a private Congregation, halting down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right betwixt Chriſt and Antichriſt in a ſhameleſs manner.</p>
            <p>Yea I am confident that ſuch-like Parſons or Lecturers, will as much gnaw their tongues, and caſt duſt upon their heads, yea cry, weep, and waile, for the loſs of Tithes, as any Presbyterian Prieſt whatſoever.</p>
            <p>Object. But you will ſay, <hi>Some mercy would be extended, in reſpect of wives and children.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115722:8"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Inaſmuch as there is a general mercy to be extended to all, you may in charity give ſomething, according as your wiſdoms ſhall think meet; but not in the leaſt, as the aforeſaid Prieſts are either Jewiſh or Popiſh Harpers, or Prelatical Muſicians, or <hi>Scotch</hi> Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipers, or the aforeſaid Independent Trumpeters, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. 22. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as they are Saylors, Craftſmen, Factors or Merchants of Romiſh wares, as in the ſaid Chapter.</p>
            <p>Object. But I am confident that ſome of you will yet reply, and ſay, <hi>What will become of the Colledges, and Lands appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> If you can finde no imployment for them, then you may ſell them.</p>
            <p>Object. But you will reply, <hi>That by ſo doing, Learning will be utterly extinguiſhed in this Commonwealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> What need is there of it? 1. In that the preſent Laws are to be no more in the Latine tongue. 2. In that Popiſh Latine Service is now out of dare; as alſo Spiritual, <hi>alias</hi> Baudy Courts. So that I know no need any Engliſh man hath to ſpeak Latine to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo conſequently Greek or Hebrew.</p>
            <p>Object. But ſome of you will reply, <hi>That the Apoſtles of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt were immediately taught by God, and therefore ſuch teaching cannot be expected from the illiterate men of the times. So that ſuch places of learning and education are very requiſite for fitting men for ſuch an imployment; as alſo, that humane learning is very neceſſary for men of ſuch imployments, in that the gift of tongues is not now given in ſuch a manner as in the Apoſtles time. As alſo, for the better underſtanding of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal texts of Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Gentlemen, I know theſe are the grand objections that you or any can make in defence of the preſent Prieſthood; which if I give you ſatisfaction in, I hope you will not any longer defer the work of God in your hands.</p>
            <p>And firſt, In relation to the gift of tongues mentioned in <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 13. where it is remarkable, that after the Apoſtles had received the ſame, they were notwithſtanding reputed by <hi>Annas</hi> the high prieſt, and <hi>Caiaphas,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> and <hi>Alexander,</hi> with the Rulers, Elders, and Scribes of Jeruſalem, to be no other then unlearned and ignorant men; ſo that this their marvelling was not at their gift of tongues,
<pb n="1" facs="tcp:115722:8"/> which they any wiſe ſaw in <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John;</hi> but meerly at their ruſtical boldneſs, and rudeneſs of ſpeech (as by miſcalling words, or the like) as is uſual with ſuch-like perſons, as daily experience teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; whereas certainly had <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> retained their <hi>quondam</hi> gift of tongues, they would no doubt have uſed better expreſſions, then ſuch as did ſo render them to be ignorant and unlearned (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially being received in ſo extraordinary a way:) which very paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is an argument ſufficient of it ſelf to ſatisfie all rational men, that the ſaid <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> had not at that time any extraordinary gift of the Spirit upon them: And if ſo, then it muſt conſequently have left them. Again, ſuch perſons as have the gift of tongues, in ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner, cannot rationally be eſteemed ignorant and unlearned perſons, which they were.</p>
            <p>Again, ſuppoſe I ſhould grant that they did ever retaine the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid donation of the gift of tongues, ſo that they could ſpeak all languages (which is as much as poſſibly you can deſire to be granted you in your friends behalf,) yet certainly you will grant me that they uſed ſuch language no otherwiſe then to edification; as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. where the Apoſtle plentifully diſcovereth the vanity of ſpeaking with tongues, unleſs to edification. And if ſo, what need is there of Latine, Greek, and Hebrew, here in <hi>England,</hi> where the whole Nation is bred up in the Engliſh tongue? And therefore why may not Engliſhmen edifie one another in the Engliſh tongue, albeit they are ignorant in the aforeſaid languages of Latine, Greek &amp; Hebrew? Yea albeit they may be as juſtly termed unlearned and ignorant men in their Engliſh or mother-tongue, as the aforeſaid <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> was in theirs.</p>
            <p>Again, have not the people of God in this Nation, the ſame im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate teachings of the Spirit, as had the Prophets and Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt? are the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament any other then the dictates of the Spirit of God? 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 19, 20, 21. Are they not the ſame in print, as they were in the Apoſtles writings; and the ſame in their writings, as they were in their words; and the ſame in their words, as they were in their thoughts; and the ſame in their thoughts, as they were in their conceptions; and the ſame in their conceptions, as in the infuſion; and the ſame in the infuſion, as they were in the Infuſor? <hi>(viz,</hi> the Holy Ghoſt) and therefore as Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt ſaith in another caſe unto his Apoſtles, <hi>He that deſpiſeth</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115722:9"/> 
               <hi>you, deſpiſeth me; and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me.</hi> So may I ſay of the printed word of God, which whoſoever deſpiſeth, deſpiſeth not only that, but alſo the Apoſtles that writ the ſame, as alſo the Holy Ghoſt it ſelf, who infuſed the ſame into their minds and thoughts; as alſo Jeſus Chriſt, and GOD the Father, from whom the ſaid Holy Ghoſt did proceed; they being a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation each to other: as printing is a manifeſtation of writing, writing of a word, and a word of a thought; ſo is the Holy Ghoſt of Jeſus Chriſt, and Jeſus Chriſt of God; and therefore to ſpeak evil of the printed Bible, is to ſpeak evil even of God himſelf, who was the Original Author thereof.</p>
            <p>Againe, are not the ſaid Scriptures appointed to that very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of edification; as alſo of inſtruction, and direction, as to the management of ſuch an office, yea, and that to every particular there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? as in the Epiſtles of <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and particularly in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16. <hi>(viz.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In that they are given by the inſpiration of the Holy Spirit, and therefore a far more excellent way of teaching the minde and will of God, then to read the conceits of heathen and Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Rhetorick, Logick, Philoſophy, and the reſt of the rabble of ſuch-like trumpery, whereof the Apoſtle exhorteth the people of God to beware. In which very things the ſtudents in Univerſities do ſpend the greateſt part of their time they can ſpare out of the Taverus and Ale-houſes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In that the Scriptures of themſelves are profitable for doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in Righteouſneſs, and that in ſuch a meaſure as to make the man of God, (whether teacher or hearer,) perfect, and thorowly furniſhed to all goods works, <hi>viz.</hi> a compleat teacher and hearer, and that to all ends and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; inſtance <hi>Timothy,</hi> whoſe very breeding in Theology was ſolely from that School-book, being trained up therein from his childhood, and not in vain Philoſophy as aforeſaid. As alſo in <hi>Apollos,</hi> who is likewiſe applauded by the Apoſtle, in that he was <hi>mighty in the Scriptures,</hi> which is able to make men <hi>wiſe unto ſalvation;</hi> and I I know no greater thing to be aimed at.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In that the Scriptures are the very meanes which Jeſus Chriſt himſelf hath appointed for that very purpoſe, as in <hi>John</hi> 5. 39. where he inviteth all men thereunto, as the chief teſtimony of him. Yea I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115722:9"/> challenge the whole tribe of the Prieſthood in this nation, to prove ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by precept or practiſe of Jeſus Chriſt and his Apoſtles, that ever there was any other courſe preſcribed, or practiſed by them, to fit or prepare labourers for Chriſts Vineyard, or worke of the holy Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery for ſucceeding times.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I would gladly know what fruits of the Spirit are to be obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Colledges, that may not be obtained out of them; or rather, what vices are there in all the Nation, that are not practiſed there? Yea, are they not the very fountains of Atheiſm, and Antihriſtianiſm, and neſts to breed ſuch ravenous Rooks in, as peſter the whole Nation by their forcing Tithes from ſuch as know it is a ſinne to pay the ſame, and that by means of your predeceſſors acts yet in force to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, yea, and that under pain of treble damages: for which things ſake, with other their unjuſt actions, their glory hath gone out like the ſnuff of a tallow Candle.</p>
            <p n="5">5. What are the Authors which their Libraries are ſtuffed withal, other then Heatheniſh and Antichriſtian? Again, is there any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe annexed to the practice of reading them? Yea, doth not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience teach, that moſt, if not all ſuch Commentaries, Expoſitions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which have been compoſed by ſuch Heathens and Antichriſtians, are found to be light as vanity? inſtance the voluminous Volumes of Philoſophers, and ancient Fathers (as they call them;) yea, ſo light, as that they are of no eſteem at all, amongſt the people of God that are come out of <hi>Babylon;</hi> which I hope you very well know: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, he that readeth the book of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> will finde that godly <hi>David</hi> became <hi>wiſer then his teachers,</hi> by reading and meditating in the <hi>Law and Prophets:</hi> And if ſo, then what need have we of other teaching then is expreſſed in the Old and New Teſtament? Certainly, he that putteth in practiſe what is there preſcribed, will finde it ſufficient to bring him to the port of heaven: whereas, as I ſaid before, the other are even rejected to be cited by the people of God as a teſtimony to the Truth. All which doth evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the teachings of men <hi>(quatenus</hi> men) to be invalid, in compariſon to the teaching of the Scriptures. And if ſo, what need is there of Univerſities to breed Divines, ſince the holy Scripture alone is ſufficient to compleat a practitioner in that Profeſſion as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; as alſo, inaſmuch as he, whoſoever of the people of God, that is able to ſpeak to the edification, exhortation, and comfort of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115722:10"/> their brethren, are compleat Prophets of God; what need have we of ſuch devouring Wolves as aforeſaid?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But I know ſome amongſt you will yet ſay, <hi>How ſhall illiterate, ignorant, and unlearned men, know the Original? which if they do not, then they muſt of neceſſity take the Tranſlation upon truſt; which Scholars do not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwer to which, I deny the concluſion: for he that can read the Bible in Engliſh, takes it no more upon truſt, then he that can read the ſame in Hebrew, Greek, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For unleſs ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons as the later can produce the very copie which <hi>Moſes</hi> writ, and have alſo compared the ſame with his preſent Tranſlation, as alſo of the Prophets and Apoſtles, they muſt of neceſſity be ſaid to take the preſent Hebrew &amp; Greek Tranſlation upon truſt, as the Engliſh man doth his Engliſh Tranſlation: for who can aver the preſent Hebrew and Greek copies to be the very ſame with the aforeſaid Original co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, unleſs they had exactly compared them with the ſaid Originals?</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, <hi>The Goſpel cannot be propagated in other Countries by the people of this Nation, if humane learning be extinguiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> My anſwer to this, is, That it is no part of my thought to blaſt humane learning, ſhould ſuch an uſe be made thereof (which as yet there hath been very little or none at all that ever I heard of) but meerly as I ſee it made uſe of to cozen and cheat the Country (as in my former inſtances to that purpoſe) and not in the leaſt to its proper edificable uſe, as intended by God as aforeſaid: for my earneſt deſire is that theſe following particulars may be proſecuted by you that are Members of this preſent Repreſentative, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 That ſuch courſe may be taken for the future in the aforeſaid Colledges or Halls in the two Univerſities, as that godly able men may be enquired after, and made uſe of, that are able to teach forraign tongues or languages.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That the aforeſaid Colledges and Halls may be ſet apart to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That the ſaid Tutor be ordered in the firſt place to tranſlate the Old and New-Teſtament into the language or tongue that they purpoſe to teach.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That after each Tutor hath ſo done, he may likewiſe read the ſame tranſlation in Engliſh, for the tryal of the truth thereof, before ſuch as ſhall be appointed for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115722:10"/> 5 That there may be ſeveral impreſſions printed of the ſaid tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That no perſons may be admitted as Students in the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges or Halls, but ſuch as the Congregational Churches ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and preſent as faithful and willing to propagate the Goſpel in ſuch Countries as uſe the language or tongue which he deſireth to ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy (if God ſhall permit him life and health<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>)</p>
            <p n="7">7 That to the aforeſaid purpoſe, every Colledge and Hall in the ſaid Univerſity may be titled or nominated according to the tongue or language that is taught therein, as, The <hi>Hebrew</hi> Colledge, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Colledge, <hi>&amp;c:</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 That the annual Revenues belonging to each of the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges or Halls, may be employed to the uſe aforeſaid, if there occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; or if too much, that then it may be diſpoſed of at your diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That ſuch Tutors, ſo ſoon as they have made their ſcholars good proficients, that then they may be ordered by you to preſent them to the Churches which preſented them, who are likewiſe to make what poſſible ſpeed they can to ſend them as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That the perſons ſo ſent may have a competent ſalary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed unto them where Providence ſhall diſpoſe of them, out of the ſaid Colledge-Land, or otherwiſe as your wiſdom ſhall think meet.</p>
            <p>Which courſe if taken, I think is as probable a way as may be to propagate the Goſpel even unto the ends of the earth, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the intended kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt as aforeſad.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But methinks I hear ſome of you yet quaery, how men may be fitted to preach the Goſpel in this Nation, if the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities be employed as aforeſaid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> I think every Engliſh man is fitted to ſpeak Engliſh by his mother, and dayly converſe with Engliſh men, ſo that it is no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then a meer cheat, to ſend Engliſh men to the Univerſities to learn to ſpeak to Engliſh men; for to what other purpoſe do the preſent Students in the ſaid Univerſities learn Latine, Greek, and Hebrew, but to preach Engliſh Sermons? And therefore I ſhall humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that ſuch as have a minde to learn ſuch languages for the future (upon any other account then to propagate the Goſpel) may do it at their own charge; and as for the Tutors, there will be no fear of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115722:11"/> want, inaſmuch as the aforeſaid locuſts and caterpillers of this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will have little elſe to do then to teach ſuch perſons.</p>
            <p>But to the end that <hi>Simeon</hi> may ſuffer as well as <hi>Levi,</hi> being bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in evil, <hi>(viz.</hi> the Lawyers of this Nation, as the Prieſts) I ſhall in the next place ſet before you, the dragonical, heatheniſh, or Kingly power of Nations over the people of God, which whilſt you likewiſe intend to continue in being, you do alſo cleerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare your ſelves Antagoniſts to the kingly government of Jeſus Chriſt; for what are the national Laws of Kings other then the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of tyrants, and corrupt men, whoſe foundation and inſtitution had their being from the corrupt reaſon of the heathen, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, laws, and puniſhments, do infinitely differ from the laws and puniſhments impoſed by God? Yea, what are they more then a meer compound of reaſon and conveniency, then ſuch as have the very image of lightneſs and corruption engraven upon them? what are they other then things full of uncertainties, and changeableneſs, then ſuch as ſtand in competition with the divine laws of God; ſuch as take no more notice of the moral and judicial laws of God, then to be a a colour for the groſs abſurdities and corruptions of the profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents therein, who cannot define the law they practiſe?</p>
            <p>Conſider therefore, I beſeech you, what a ſhame it will be unto you, if you henceforth countenance ſuch laws and lawyers in the leaſt, ſeeing they are the very brood or off-ſpring of the heatheniſh Dragon mentioned, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12. as alſo inaſmuch as your ſelves and predeceſſors have ſo manifeſtly declared your ſelves in the higheſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt the Original Authors and promoters thereof; as alſo in that they are ſo diametrically oppoſite to the aforeſaid Sacred and Divine Laws inſtituted by the everlaſting God himſelf, whoſe ſervants you profeſs your ſelves to be in point of Obedience to the ſame.</p>
            <p>As alſo in as much as the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> affirmeth, that there is but one Law-giver to the people of God, <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. 12. which the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> rendereth to be the Lord <hi>Jehovah,</hi> where ſpeaking of the exaltation of the Kingdome of Jeſus Chriſt, and the ſpoiling and ruinating of the adverſaries thereof, he ſaith, <hi>Wo unto thee that ſpoileſt, and thou waſt not ſpoiled, and dealeſt treacherouſly, and they did not deal treacherouſly with thee:</hi> (therefore, ſaith he) <hi>when thou ſhalt ceaſe to ſpoile, thou ſhalt be ſpoiled; when thou</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115722:11"/> 
               <hi>ſhalt make an end to deal treacherouſly, they ſhall deal treacher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly with thee; (viz.</hi> when the limited time appointed for their ſo doing is accompliſhed: not that they would otherwiſe willingly ceaſe, either to ſpoile or deal treacherouſly with the Saints of the moſt High God:) a Chapter worthy your moſt ſerious reading and meditation, (as alſo the precedent and following) where, in <hi>verſ.</hi> 22. the Prophet declareth, that at the accompliſhment of the aforeſaid judgements, that <hi>Then the Lord himſelf will become judge unto his people, as alſo their Law-giver, and their King, and their Saviour.</hi> And if ſo, then there ought not to be two Law-makers, muchleſs a compound of the Law of God, and the corrupt reaſon of <hi>William the Conqueror,</hi> or any either before or after him, who have dealt with the moral and judicial law of God, even as Antichriſt, or that whore of <hi>Rome</hi> hath dealt with the injunctions of Jeſus Chriſt in the Goſpel, ſcruing them to ſuite with their Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon-like, and whoriſh pleaſures in all things; the one ſetting up cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt reaſon in ſtead of that reaſon which was incorrupt; and the other an aboliſhed Prieſthood, with the appendances thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, in ſtead of that which then was, and is as permanent as Mount Sion, which cannot be removed: by which Tyrannical and ſubtil practice of the aforeſaid Dragon or Beaſt, on which the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid whore is ſaid to ſit, they have been the death of many millions of the Saints of the Moſt High. Whereas I affirme, that the life of no man ought to be taken away by any other Law, then of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Law-giver, who alone is able to ſave and to deſtroy, as in <hi>James</hi> 4. 12. as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Againe, Reaſon it ſelf teacheth, that he that gave the life, hath only the power to take it away by his own laws; and if ſo, then not by the laws of any the aforeſaid perſons whatſoever. Conſider then what judgement and puniſhment have our Judges incurred to themſelves by taking away the lives of men for ſimple theft! whereas, according to the Laws of God, they ought not to have dyed, but to have made reſtitution; and therefore without controverſie, a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful wo will light upon you, if you repeal not that law before you ſend the (otherwiſe mercileſs) Judges to ſit in judicature upon ſuch perſons; no mans life being to be taken away otherwiſe then by the direct law of the aforeſaid onely Law-giver, and that by particular precept, or General Rule.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115722:12"/>
            <p> For if you be Chriſtians, then are you no other then Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; and if ſo, then are you bound in duty and conſcience to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute juſtice only according to the will of God, and not according to any different lawes made by the aforeſaid perſons, that have onely uſurped that Soveraign power unto themſelves, to take away the lives of men at their pleaſure, or luſts, or malice of their own hearts, or any private revenge of their own or others. For as the Apoſtle ſaith in another caſe, It is requiſite in Stewards, that they be found faithful, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 2. but the will of God in point of judicature, appeareth not otherwiſe then in his word. And therefore inaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as that which is not of Faith <hi>(viz.</hi> firme perſwaſion) is ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 23. As alſo, inaſmuch as faith ought to be grounded upon the word of God, as being wrought thereby, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 17. how can ſuch Acts of juſtice be either approved in the ſight of God, or good men, as are not warranted by the ſaid word? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by how much you permit any laws, that differed from the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid precepts or preſidents in Scripture, by ſo much you do abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare your ſelves to be the brood of the aforeſaid Pagan or ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical Dragon, which is ſaid to perſecute the Church or people of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. and that as much as if you your ſelves had contrived the ſame. Yea, I appeal to impudence it ſelf, whether the aforeſaid judicial laws of God be not the beſt expoſitors of the moral law. And if ſo, what is there wanting in the moral law, that is requiſite to a Commonwealth, either in the Negative or Affirmative part thereof?</p>
            <p>Again, inaſmuch as the ſaid judicial Law is not in the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, why ought it not to be in the like repute with you, as it was to the ancient people of God, unto whom it was firſt delivered <hi>(viz.</hi> the Jews) ſeeing that it cannot be denyed, that believing Gentiles, are as well the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> (which the Apoſtle affirmeth, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 9. 23.) and ſo conſequently Jews aſwel as they; yea, and that in a far more tranſcendent relation, by how much the unbelieving Jews are eſteemed no Jews, in compariſon of the other, as the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle likewiſe affirmeth. And therefore according to Captaine <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woods</hi> rule, though quite contrary to his opinion, (in that he claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the aforeſaid laws of corrupt reaſon as his fathers patrimony, and therefore ſetteth an invaluable eſteem of them in his late book, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> I ſay, in the behalf of the aforeſaid moral and judicial laws of God
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115722:12"/> our Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that we will have no other laws then them, inaſmuch as they are our birthright and patrimony; as alſo in that it is our heavenly Fathers will that we ſhould be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent thereunto, even as it was the will of <hi>Jonadab</hi> the ſon of <hi>Rechab'</hi> that his ſons ſhould drink no wine; as alſo in that they are as well now the mark of diſtinction betwixt the people of God and heathens, as they were betwixt the Jews and the Gentiles, at the time of the giving thereof; and therefore you are bound in duty and ſervice to propagate the ſame, and annihilate the other, which Captain <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> would ſo gladly have preſerved, bidding defiance even to God himſelf to alter them (in a moſt impious manner) whereas there is not one text of Scripture that giveth liberty to any Magiſtrate whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, either to add or detract from the aforeſaid Laws, or anywiſe to alter them, as to fit them with their humour, either as to point of time, or manner of the Country where they live. And if not, then doth it not argue a groſs preſumption in thoſe that do ſo? yea do they not by ſuch means take upon them to be wiſer then God himſelf, by ſuch their altering and leaving thoſe directions and rules of juſtice, which he hath ſet down as irrevocably unalterable, in reſpect to man, in the leaſt <hi>Iota</hi> or tittle thereof, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. 17, 18, 19. and that upon pain of incurring the diſpleaſure of the great God of heaven and earth? As alſo, inaſmuch as the fooliſhneſs of God is wiſer then the wiſdom of men, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 25. yea ſurpaſſing the deepeſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties or State-policies in the world.</p>
            <p>Again, Is it not the boaſting of the ſupporters and practitioners of our preſent Heatheniſh Laws, that they are founded upon the laws of God? and if ſo, I would gladly know of them what laws of God they mean, if not the aforeſaid lawes. Yea, certainly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them will be ready to confeſs the ſame, and think they much honor the preſent lawes by ſo ſaying: And if ſo, then how dare any of them to ſlight any one tittle of them Lawes, which they have hitherto ſo much magnified for their own advantage?</p>
            <p>Judge therefore I pray you, wherefore it is that they have not made uſe of the Original it ſelf, from whence they ſay the preſent laws are derived <hi>(viz.</hi> whether it be becauſe the laws of God are leſs politick, or <hi>leſs profitable,</hi> leſs tedious, or <hi>leſs chargable,</hi> leſs inconſiſtent with the mind and will of God, or the mind and will of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſupporters or practitioners therein.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115722:13"/>
            <p> Again, Did not the judicial law of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſerve to decide all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies tending to the violation of the moral law? and is it not now as able to ſerve us to the like purpoſe? But put the caſe it ſhould not be able ſo to do, are we therefore left at liberty to cut and chuſe, to puniſh that fault with death, which is appointed by God to be healed by reſtitution; and that crime with purſe-puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the which death was to be inflicted, and ſo to add and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh at pleaſure?</p>
            <p>No certainly, in ſuch caſes we are in no wiſe permitted by God to diminiſh one tittle thereof, but rather to ſupply what is defective therein. But there is no ground for any ſuch jealouſie to ariſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people of God, as to think the ſaid law to be deficient in the leaſt, it having the character of perfection ſtamped upon it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. 7. yea to be holy, juſt, and good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 12. Yea doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſuch a law, as if put in practice by you, (which I do hereby in the name of God adjure you to do) would doubtleſs be a chief means under God to convert his antient people the Jews, we receiving their law, they our Goſpel; we their <hi>Moſes,</hi> they our Chriſt: which happy conjunction was certainly predicted at the transfiguration of Jeſus Chriſt in the mount, where <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias (viz.</hi> the Law and the Prophets) are ſaid to aſſociate, and bear teſtimony of him, as well as the word or voice from heaven (or his Church.) Yea, even in that his glorified condition, which doubtleſs did typifie his rule and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in his Monarchical kingdome as aforeſaid; at which time there ſhould be a ſweet concurrence and harmony betwixt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Saints and Jews a fitter obligation then which to unite them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I think cannot be imagined; and which once effected, would be the greateſt earthly glory to the Saints of God in General that ever was yet attained; as alſo to the Angels in heaven, who doubtleſs would alſo very much rejoyce thereat.</p>
            <p>Now for the better underſtanding of my meaning, touching the aforeſaid judicial Law, It is to be obſerved, that in the writings of <hi>Moſes,</hi> there are divers ſorts of laws, as the Ceremonial and Judicial Laws; which Ceremonial Law is wholly aboliſhed by Chriſt, they being only types and ſhadows of his bodily ſubſtance, which when once come, the other was to be done away by gradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, until he gave up the Ghoſt, ſaying, <hi>It is finiſhed;</hi> at which time it was wholly accompliſhed and abrogated, with all its appendancies.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115722:13"/>
            <p> Again, the judicials are of three ſorts, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Such as are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the moral Law, as the puniſhment of Adultery and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and diſobedience to Parents with death, and ſuch like. 2 Or ſuch as were appendant to the Ceremonial Law, as the puniſhment of thoſe that touched any dead thing, or that came neer a woman in her monthly courſes, and ſuch-like. 3 Or ſuch as belonged to that peculiar policy and State of that Commonweath, as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the year of Jubilee, the raiſing up ſeed to the brother departed, in marrying his wife, and the like.</p>
            <p>Of which two latter there is no doubt, but the firſt is abrogated, together with the Ceremonies whereon they attended; the other, as proper to that Government, is alſo now determined: for otherwiſe the like courſe muſt be now taken for raiſing of ſeed as was then; which Law Jeſus Chriſt affirmeth that <hi>Moſes</hi> made meerly <hi>becauſe of the hardneſs of the Jews hearts;</hi> as in the caſe of the woman that had ſeven husbands, <hi>which</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>from the beginning was not ſo;</hi> there being then but one woman to one man, and one man to one woman; and ſo doubtleſs moſt, if not all the Laws of that tenure.</p>
            <p>So that the third kinde of Judicial remaineth onely to be put in practice, about which this following Quaery doth ariſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quaere. <hi>Whether the puniſhment inflicted by</hi> Moſes <hi>for the breach of the moral Law, together with the moral Law is impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by God upon all Chriſtian Magiſtrates, ſo that they are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>In that by ſuch a practice, it would quite overthrow the policy and inſtitution of this preſent Commonwealth, which for a long time hath continued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>In that our Saviour commanded to give tribute to</hi> Caeſar, <hi>by which act he did enjoyn obedience to thoſe higher powers, which did at that time bear the ſword, albeit they were Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Inaſmuch as our Saviour himſelf obſerved not the judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als belonging to the Moral Law: for where he that gathered ſticks on the Sabbath-day, was ſtoned to death by</hi> Moſes; <hi>Our Saviour excuſeth and defendeth his Apoſtles, who did as much as in effect, by plucking up ears of corn on the Sabbath day, and rubbing them in their hand for their ſuſtenance,</hi> Mat. 12.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115722:14"/> 4 <hi>In that he giveth a rule that it was not lawful for a man to put away his wife,</hi> except <hi>for the cauſe of Fornication and Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery;</hi> Mat. 19. <hi>which</hi> exception <hi>needed not, if either in fact then, or in right afterwards, Adulterers and Adultereſſes were then to be put to death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 <hi>In that he alſo ſuffered the woman taken in the very act of Adultery to eſcape without puniſhment of death,</hi> Joh. 8.</p>
            <p n="6">6 <hi>In that the continual practice ſheweth that there was no Law in force at that time to put ſuch like malefactors to death, inſtance alſo the inceſtuous perſon,</hi> 1 Cor. 5. <hi>which the Apoſtle willeth onely to be excommunicated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Touching the impoſition of the aforeſaid Laws, in relation to the eſſential parts thereof, that they are not left to the liberty of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate to add any thing thereunto, or to take from it, or in the leaſt to alter it (ſo as ſhall be thought meet for the preſent time or manner of the Country) I think I have formerly ſaid enough to ſatisfie any rational man, as that by giving way thereunto, they would not onely grapple with God himſelf in point of wiſdom, but that they would alſo thereby put themſelves into ſuch a condition, as that they might altogether leave thoſe divine Laws, Commandments and rules of Juſtice (and that at pleaſure) which the Lord God of heaven and earth hath ſet down for a rule and direction to obſerve, and contrary whereunto they cannot be approved in the ſight of God or godly men.</p>
            <p>2 As concerning the practice thereof, whereas it is alleadged that the putting in execution of the aforeſaid judicials, would quite over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn all the policy and inſtitution of the preſent Commonwealth; I anſwer, that it is to that very end and purpoſe, that I do propound the ſame, to be put in execution by you.</p>
            <p>For by how much you retain the preſent policy and inſtitution of this Commonwealth, by ſo much you bid defiance to the aforeſaid Laws of God himſelf, as I have plentifully proved.</p>
            <p>3 Whereas it is alleadged that neither Jeſus Chriſt or his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or ſucceſſors did ever yet aſſume the power to put the aforeſaid Laws in execution; I anſwer, that the aforeſaid perſons have ever been under reſtraint, as captives or ſojourners, and therefore were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways under the Laws of them that were Lords over them, <hi>(viz.</hi> heatheniſh Magiſtrates) and therefore were in no wiſe permitted to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115722:14"/> make uſe of the aforeſaid Laws of God. As in the time of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his abode upon earth, doth cleerly appear, by the Anſwer which the people of the Jews, (whom the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Laws properly concerned) gave unto <hi>Pilate</hi> (at the arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Jeſus Chriſt before him in point of blaſphemy) where they tell him, <hi>that by their Law they could put no man to death;</hi> No not for that very crime of blaſphemy, which they accuſed him of: which doth cleerly import, that the Scepter was then departed from <hi>Judah,</hi> and a Law-giver from betwixt his feet, the promiſed Meſſiah being then come and amongſt them, albeit they were ignorant thereof, and yet are to this preſent day.</p>
            <p>4 Whereas it is alleadged that Jeſus Chriſt himſelf did not pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice according to the ſaid Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I Reply, That it was becauſe, as a man, he was under reſtraint as the reſt of the Nation of the Jews, and therefore had no more power then they to null or make void the then preſent Laws of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> 2 in that his kingdom was not of that preſent world, he being at that time in a ſuffering condition, his then appearing in the fleſh being onely as an example of patience to all his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>So that all the former objections do not in the leaſt prove that the aforeſaid Laws are in the leaſt aboliſhed: and if not the Laws, then conſequently not the aforeſaid judicial puniſhments; for by how much the Law of God was then reſtrained, by ſo much the ſaid pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment was not put in practice: but this reſtraint was to continue but its appointed ſeaſon, <hi>viz.</hi> until ſuch times as Jeſus Chriſts world ſhould be made apparent, in which he ſhould reign as King over the face of the whole earth, according to the afore mentioned propheſies: which kingdom I judge took place, as ſoon as the fatal blow was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to the late King; which being done, immediately the late Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did utterly renounce the Government of this Nation by Kings as Tyrants, as appears in the Old Exchange, where over the place where the late Kings Portraicture was fixed, is ingraven, <hi>Exit Tyrannus.</hi> Which doth cleerly import a change of the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from ſuch Kings as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> defired to be governed by, in 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. 5. unto that Government which they were formerly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by, as by Judges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo conſequently of the Laws, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaying, <hi>New Lords, New Laws:</hi> which did alſo cleerly appear by the late Act of Adultery, where they made the ſin
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115722:15"/> puniſhable by death: which doth cleerly manifeſt that the late late Parliament was carryed on, though in darkneſs, to put in execution the aforeſaid Laws of God: inſtance the alſo the late Act of the Lord General (if as reported) in not permitting Simple Theft to be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by death. Which are two evident teſtimonies that the Lord is ſtedfaſtly purpoſed to promote his own Laws in ſtead of the preſent Laws of the Nation.</p>
            <p>And therefore if you will ſet your ſelves with all your might to proſecute the ſame, you will thereby be made famous to all poſterity: for thereby you will not onely be made Conquerors over the whole earth, as in the aforeſaid Prophecies, but will alſo be inſtrumental to the converſion of the ancient people of God, <hi>(viz.</hi> the Jews.)</p>
            <p>Yea, I dare aver, that if you will ſet your ſelves to the aforeſaid work with a cordial reſolution to erect the aforeſaid Laws of God, and Ordinances of Jeſus Chriſt, you will ſtrike as great a terrour into all the Nations about, as the Iſraelites did to the Canaanites, or <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to <hi>Nabal,</hi> when he marched againſt him. For, indeed, what fleſh dares oppoſe the Laws of their Maker, and the Ordinances of their Redeemer?</p>
            <p>And therefore I beſeech you deal uprightly, and with a ſincere heart, in the great work of God before you, even as in the preſence of God: and be not like your predeceſſors, with <hi>a heart and a heart;</hi> one for Chriſt, and another for Antichriſt; with a heart to aboliſh Prelacie, and not Presbytery; to take away Biſhops, Deans and Chapters lands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet to retain Presbytery and their Tythes; with a heart to puniſh the ſeventh Commandment according to the puniſhment appointed by God, and not all the reſt of the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. For be you well aſſured, that if you halt (as did your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors) betwixt light and darkneſs, Chriſt and Antichriſt, God and Mammon, like the luke-warm <hi>Laodicean,</hi> and that either through the corruption of your own hearts, or the ſubtil, politick, and Jeſuitical deſignes, inſtigations, or allurements of any your neereſt and deareſt friends or alliance in the whole world; the Lord will as well <hi>ſpue you out,</hi> as he did your predeceſſors, of whom it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, That <hi>they were Sermon-proof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be expected by any, that I ſhould have drawn the aforeſaid Laws and Puniſhments into a method, I anſwer, that I have forborn the ſame, in that they will very ſhortly be publiſhed in print by an
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115722:15"/> able man, who hath extracted the ſame, and is now ready for the Preſs.</p>
            <p>I deſire therefore, that that which I have here written may not be ſlighted, becauſe it doth not proceed from one that is eminent, or adorned with Titles of Honour, or in a great place of Truſt; for <hi>Solomon</hi> telleth you of <hi>a poor wiſe man,</hi> that did every way equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize the greateſt Magiſtrates in the City where he lived, in point of wiſdom, albeit they were too ſtately to take any notice of it; which he eſteemeth as one of the <hi>evils which he perceived under the ſun,</hi> and that <hi>a great one,</hi> Eccleſ. 9. 13, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Again, peradventure ſome of you will think I have been too bold with you, as you are the Supreme power of the Nation. And if ſo, I muſt reply with <hi>David</hi>'s words, <hi>The righteous are as bold as lions,</hi> and <hi>will not fear what man can do unto them.</hi> Beſides, it is not the firſt time that I have put Magiſtrates in minde of their duty, as will appear by my book titled <hi>Rome ruined by White-hall,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In the Preface to which Book, I told the late Parliament that they were like to <hi>Martha, cumbred with much buſineſs,</hi> (by reaſon of the clamours of the people, whoſe chief affections were taken up in obtaining a flouriſhing ſtate, with the appurtenances thereunto, <hi>viz.</hi> a full trade, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> but that there was but <hi>one thing neceſſary,</hi> which was far from the peoples thoughts, and (I feared) not very neer theirs, <hi>viz.</hi> the erecting of the Kingdom of Jeſus Chriſt, which I ſaid ought to be their chief object, in that the other would fall of courſe, as our bleſſed Saviour affirmeth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 33. a Chapter worthy your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious meditations, in this your preſent employment: for doubtleſs Providence doth as well extend it ſelf over the whole Nation, as over one particular perſon, or ſparrow, or hair of a mans head. But ſuch is the frail condition of our natures, that we dare not truſt God with our temporals.</p>
            <p>I did alſo, in minding them of the Clergie of the Nation, uſe theſe following expreſſions, <hi>viz. Sure it is, you have found that Tribe as much averſe to your proceedings, as, had you not been valiant, might have utterly obſtructed the work of God in your hands.</hi> And withal told them, <hi>that ſo long as they permitted ſuch</hi> Judas<hi>'s, it was impoſſible that the State ſhould ever be in quiet: ſo that they muſt either reſolve to ſuppreſs them, or to be ſuppreſſed by them.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115722:16"/>
            <p> To which purpoſe, I did alſo at that time admoniſh them to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtir themſelves like men of valour, by giving them a full overturn, and that both root and branch; as alſo by giving way to ſuch ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of Churches, as did practice according to the rule preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in Gods word, So that the true Churches and Miniſters of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt might be diſtinguiſhed from them of <hi>Aarons</hi> order; and withall told them, that in ſo doing we ſhould be put into the like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as were the people of God at <hi>Antioch,</hi> where the Diſciples were firſt called Chriſtians; and thereby not only bring glory to the Nation, but alſo immortalize their names to all poſterities; as alſo that Jeſus Chriſt had been ſo pleaſed to make them the firſt tender of honour to reſtore his Church to the Primitive purity thereof, which was a thing they had very often engaged themſelves to performe. Whereupon in the Epilogue to the ſaid book, I admoniſhed them in theſe following verſes, ſaying,</p>
            <l>And therefore hear, O Kings and Rulers all;</l>
            <l>Harke with attendance, liſten to the call</l>
            <l>That doth invite you for to entertain</l>
            <l>Chriſt for your King, who is reſolv'd to reign</l>
            <l>'Ore you and yours, either by love, or aw,</l>
            <l>But rather doth deſire that love may draw</l>
            <l>Your hearts for to comply to bear his yoak:</l>
            <l>If not, then know, there is a heavy ſtroak</l>
            <l>To be laid on you, with an iron rod,</l>
            <l>Even by the hand of a provoked God,</l>
            <l>The which will cruſh your power, and make you know,</l>
            <l>That as in things above, ſo here below,</l>
            <l>He hath the Kingly power, and will direct</l>
            <l>All ſuch as he intendeth to protect.</l>
            <p>And hath not the ſame been compleatly fulfilled upon them, for their negligence therein? And therefore I deſire once more, that you would learn by their harmes to beware, leaſt the ſame puniſhment befal you, as it hath done them; which the Lord, in much mercy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, by making you ſuch perſons as is mentioned in my Epiſtle to the Reader, <hi>viz.</hi> ſuch as are clothed with the white robes of the Lambe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:115722:16"/> Chriſt Jeſus, to the end the prediction at the cloſe of that Epiſtle may be accompliſhed by you, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <l>
               <hi>Take notice</hi> Rome, <hi>even in the ſame White-Hall,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Where here thou hadſt thy Riſe, thou haſt thy fall.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer/>
            <postscript>
               <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF any deſire the Book, they may have it at</hi> Giles Calverts <hi>Shop at the Black-ſpread Eagle, at the Weſt end of</hi> Pauls.</p>
            </postscript>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
